Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection, 1780-1783: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
- Series 2: March of the French Army from Providence to Virginia, March 1781 - October 1781, 10 portfolios (1 partial)
  - Figuré de la Route et des differents Camps que l'Armée Françoise a occupé depuis Providence jusqu'à la réunion des deux Armées au Camp de Philips-burg, undated; more than 13 packets 23 x 16 cm (dimensions of cahier when closed; the fold-out sheets are of varying width) (Portfolio VII, Packet 14)
    - 24. Onzième Journée. Le 3 juillet de Ridgebury a Nord castel, 22 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 51 cm (including hinged square, upper right) (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-11)
      Eleventh Day's March: from Ridgebury [in Connecticut] to North Castle [in New York]. \ 3 July 1781. While the French were camped at Ridgebury, orders were received for a change of itinerary. Instead of proceeding westward from Ridgebury to join the Americans at Peekskill on the Hudson, as originally planned, the French army now veered to the southwest to join their allies at Philipsburg. The First Brigade, leaving Ridgebury on 2 July, bivouacked at Bedford (present Bedford Village) and proceeded next day to the camp at North Castle (present Mount Kisco, Westchester County, New York). The Second Brigade covered the whole distance from Ridgebury to North Castle, by a slightly different route, in a single day's march on 3 July 1781. This road map shows only the route of the Second Brigade. The "Pond" indicated midway along the route is Lake Waccabuc. The bridge over the Cross River is now inundated by the Cross River Reservoir. The "justice," noted along the route between Cross River and North Castle, indicates a gallows, commemorated in the present name of Hangman's Hill.
      MS, No. 14-11. [Rice/Brown, pp. 130-131]
      Regarding change of itinerary, see Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, nn. 31-32, and Berthier's journal, p. 248.
    - 25. Douzième Journée. Le 6. Marche par armée et reunion des deux armées Le 6 Juillet 1781 au camp de Philipp's burg occupant la position cy marqué. de Nord castle à Philip's-burg, 22 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 57 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-12)
      Twelfth Day's March: from North Castle to Philipsburg. On 6 July 1781 the French army marched in a single column from its camp at North Castle (Mount Kisco) south to Philipsburg, where it joined the American army. The Philipsburg camp, where the allied armies remained until 18-19 August, was on the heights between the Bronx and Sawmill river within the limits of the present town of Greenburgh, Westchester County, New York.
      The right column of the French army followed this route again, in the opposite direction, when marching northward to King's Ferry, 19 August 1781. See Itinerary 3.
      MS, No. 14-12. [Rice/Brown, p. 131]
  - Road Maps of the French Army's March from the Hudson to Virginia, August - September, 1781, dates not examined; more than 18 packets 23 x 16 cm (dimensions of cahier when closed; the fold-out sheets are of varying width) (Portfolio VIII, Packet 15)
    This is another series of road maps (no other copies of which have been found) showing the army's route from the Hudson to the head of Chesapeake Bay.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 15 (1-6)
    - 48. March from Newcastle, via Pines Bridge and Crompond, to King's Ferry and Stony Point, Including a Plan of West Point, dates not examined; 1 item 22.5 (27.5 with fold-out extension, upper right) x 54.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 15-1)
      20-25 August 1781. New Castle to Stony Point and West Point - with details of the 18 batteries and redoubts around West Point, and a drawing below showing A) Profile of the wooden redouts constructed at West Point ["Profil des redoutes en bois construites à West-point."] and B) Profile of an entrance to Fort Clinton where a countersink was relieved and the entrance was closed ["Profil d'une embrazure du Fort Clinton dont les fraizes se relèvent et ferment l'embrazure."]
      Leaving the Philipsburg camp on 18-19 August 1781, the French army proceeded northward in two columns to Pines Bridge on the Croton River and thence in a single column to King's Ferry, while the American army marched via New Bridge at the mouth of the Croton over a route closer to the Hudson. There is no new map for the first march from Philipsburg to North Castle (Mount Kisco), but No. 25, showing the southward march on 6 July, indicates the route over which the right column of the French army retraced its steps in the opposite direction some six weeks later.
      The map reproduced here represents the second, third, and fourth marches extending over the period 20-25 August. The portion at far left traces the road over Crow Hill from North Castle (not shown) to Pines Bridge on the Croton River. "New-castl," used in the inscription, designated the general area and is now the name of the township of Newcastle, established in 1791. Between the Croton River and "Crompton" (present town of Yorktown) is the Hunt's Tavern camp (shown on the map, but not so designated); cf. No. 61. The next encampment at Verplank's Point near the eastern end of King's Ferry, also shown here, is depicted in greater detail in the series of camp maps, No. 62. Finally, across the Hudson, beyond the Stony Point peninsula, is the so-called Haverstraw camp (present village of Stony Point), also depicted in the campsite maps, No. 63.
      This map is extended to include The Highlands and a plan of West Point, though the army's route did not pass through the area north of Peekskill. General Rochambeau and several of his officers, accompanied by Washington, visited the key American stronghold on 23 August.
      MS, No. 15-1. [Rice/Brown, pp. 141-142]
      The marches from Philipsburg to King's Ferry are described in detail in the journals of both Clermont-Crèvecœur and Berthier (pp. 40-42 and 253-55, respectively) as well as in Itinerary 3.
      See Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, p. 41 and n. 57. Other maps showing West Point at approximately this same time are: Crublier d'Opterre MS No. 15, Library of Paul Mellon, Historical Society of Pennsylvania, Cromot Dubourg journal (reproduced in the Magazine of American History, IV, No. 4 [April 1880], between 304 and 305); Service Historique do la Marine, Fonds du Service Hydrographique, MS No. 2847, Cromot Dubourg's "Atlas," No. 5; Library of Congress, Map Division, "Plan de West-Pointe du Nord" (reproduced in Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress, XXVIII, No. 3 [July 1971], 213).
    - 49. de Haver-strow à Suffrans, 16 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 31 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 15-2)
      March from Haverstraw to Suffern. 25-26 August 1781.This was the first march after the crossing of the Hudson at King's Ferry, made on successive days by the First Brigade (including the Bourbonnais and Deux-Ponts regiments) and Second Brigade (including the Soissonnais and Saintonge). The route led from the Haverstraw camp (i.e., Stony Point village) via Kakiat (present New Hempstead, Rockland County, New York) to Suffern, New York. Kakiat ("meeting house," "Coff taverne," "Keycit place" on map) was a pivotal point on the eighteenth-century routes leading from the Hudson into northern New Jersey: the "lower road," indicated here, went south along the Saddle River to Paramus and the Jersey lowlands, while the upper road taken by the French army went via Suffern into the Ramapo Valley, which was protected by mountains on the east. Suffern was likewise an important road junction: the road from New Windsor, north of West Point and The Highlands, via The Clove, came in here.
      In preparation for the march through New Jersey, Jeremiah Wadsworth and John Carter (Church), purchasing agents for the French army, instructed their agent, David Reynolds, to assemble supplies (15 tons of hay, 20 tons of straw, 230 bushels of corn, 5 cords of wood) at each of the following "staging posts": Suffern, Pompton, Whippany, Bullion's Tavern, Somerset Courthouse, and Princeton.
      MS, No 15-2. [Rice/Brown, pp. 142-143]
      Earlier road surveys of this region (now in the New-York Historical Society) prepared under the direction of Robert Erksine, geographer to Washington's army, which were probably available to the French, provide a useful complement to the Berthier road maps; cf. Peter J. Guthorn, American Maps and Map Makers of the Revolution (Monmouth Beach, N.J., 1966), pp. 17ff. See also Washington's letter of 29 August 1781 to Simeon DeWitt (Erksine's successor), Writings of GW, XXIII, 68-69: "Immediately upon receipt of this you will begin to Survey the road... to Princeton, thence (through Maidenhead) to Trenton, thence to Philadelphia, thence to the head of Elk through Darby, Chester, Wilmington, Christian Bridge. At the head of Elk, you will receive further orders... ."
      See Wadsworth and Carter to Reynolds, Philipsburg, 18 August 1781, in Wadsworth Papers (Connecticut Historical Society), Box 153, Letterbook B, p. 108, for material relating to activity of purchasing agents Wadsworth and Carter.
    - 50. de Suffrans à Pompton, 12 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 26.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 15-3)
      March from Suffern [in New York] to Pompton [in New Jersey]. 26-27 August 1781. The route along the Ramapo Valley corresponds closely to present U.S. Route 202. "Pompton," the terminus of this march, is the locality now known as Pompton Plains. The curious words "her scaller house," designating a property between Pond's Church and the Pompton River, is a draftsman's miscopying of "Mr. [Casparus] Schuyler's House." "Bartoli moulin" is probably Bartolf's (or Bertolf's) Mill; "Fanallen's Mills," Van Allen's.
      MS, No. 15-3. [Rice/Brown, p. 143]
      The March through New Jersey is described in Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal (pp. 42ff.) and in Itineraries 3 and 4.
    - 51. de Pompton à Wippany, 15 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 29.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 15-4)
      March from Pompton to Whippany: 27-29 August 1781. The First Brigade halted here an extra day, not leaving until the 29th; the whole army was thus camped at Whippany on the 28th. The upper branches of the Passaic River are sketched here in pencil; "fork," under the word "Whippany" in the heading, indicates present Two Bridges, at the confluence of the Pompton and Passaic river. "Ferme de Mr. Lot," to the left of Troy Town on the map, is Beverwyck, the estate of Lucas von Beverhoudt, then also the residence of Abraham Lott, a patriot refugee from New York City. See Itinerary 3, p. 57 and n. 36.
      MS, No. 15-4. [Rice/Brown, p. 143]
    - 52. de Wippany à Bullion's tavern, 14 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 28.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 15-5)
      March from Whippany to Bullion's Tavern. 29-30 August 1781. "Hanover's Vll. [Village]" at the left of the map is the locality to the west of Whippany now known as Monroe; Whippany, an ancient settlement never incorporated separately, is still part of Hanover Township. The "Mill" shown here forms the present boundary between Morris and Somerset counties. The "Maison du lord Sterling" was the estate of WIlliam Alexander ("Lord Stirling"), southeast of Basking RIdge, near the site of the present Somerset Hills Airport. Bullion's (or Bolan's) Tavern was at present Liberty Corner. It was at this point in the march that the troops began to realize that they would not be attacking the British in New York via Staten Island but that Virginia was their destination.
      MS, No. 15-5. [Rice/Brown, p. 144]
    - 53. de Bullion's tavern à Summerset court house, 13 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 29 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 15-6)
      March from Bullion's Tavern to Somerset Courthouse. 30-31 August 1781. The "Black-men road," left of map, is the road to Pluckemin. The "montagne très roide et très longue à monter" is the Second Watchung Mountain, north of present Martinsville. The descent over First Watchung Mountain down into the Raritan Valley was via Steele's Gap, as described above in Itinerary 4. "Vinvington house" is the Van Veghton house, near Van Veghtan's Bridge (the present bridge at Manville, State Route 553). Somerset Courthouse is present Millstone on the river of that name; the county seat was later moved to Somerville.
      MS, No. 15-6. [Rice/Brown, p. 144]
    - 54. de Summerset court house à Prince-town, 13 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 27.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 16-1)
      March from Somerset Courthouse to Princeton. 31 August - 1 September 1781. The "Mill" at left of map, then belonging to Archibald Mercer, is the locality subsequently known as Blackwell's Mills. The route crossed to the east bank of the Millstone River at Griggstown (not named here) where several taverns are shown. The Delaware and Raritan Canal now runs parallel to this part of the Millstone. The army's route recrossed to the west side of the river at Rocky Hill (not named on map) and thence to Princeton via Mount Lucas Road, the last strech of which is now called Witherspoon Street. The property shown across the road (present Stockton Street) from the army's campsite is "Morven," then the residence of Annis Boudinot, widow of Richard Stockton, "The Signer," who had died earlier that year.
      Describing the army's march from Princeton to Somerset Courthouse a year later (8 September 1782), Von Closen notes (p. 235): "We did not take the same road as the previous year, but a new passage was opened up along the Millstone River which was on our right [i.e., when going North] all the way."
      MS, No. 16-1. [Rice/Brown, p. 144]
    - 55. de Prince-town à Trenton, 12 1\2 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 27 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 16-2)
      March from Princeton to Trenton. 1-2 September 1781. The route follows closely present U.S. Route 206. "Stony brug Hameau," at left of map, indicates the "hamlet" at Stony Brook (Worth's Mill), one of the earliest settlements (ca. 1700) in what later became the town of Princeton. "Maidenhead" is present Lawrenceville, so renamed in honor of Captain James Lawrence, naval hero of the War of 1812. At Trenton two ferries are shown below the falls: Trenton Ferry, which crossed the Delaware from the foot of Ferry Street near the present Pennsylvania Railroad bridge, and Continental Ferry, lower down, which crossed from a point below the present site of Riverview Cemetery (Lamberton Road).
      MS, No. 16-2. [Rice/Brown, pp. 144-145]
    - 56. de Trenton à Read-lion's Tavern, 16 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 29 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 16-3)
      March from Trenton to Red Lion Tavern. 2-3 September 1781. The army had now reached Pennsylvania. The river to the right of Bristol on the map is the Neshaminy. As indicated in Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal (p. 45), the artillery crossed it at a ford, several miles upstream, while the infantry used the ferry. Dr. James Thatcher, who was marching with the American army at the same time, notes in his Military Journal {Boston, 1823), p. 325, that on 1 September "we crossed a small river at Shammany's rope ferry. Our boats were pulled across with facility by a rope made fast at each shore." Red Lion Tavern, the terminus of this march, was on present U.S. Route 13, at Poquessing Creek, which now forms the northern boundary of the City (and County) of Philadelphia.
      MS, No. 16-3. [Rice/Brown, p. 145]
    - 57. de Read-lion's tavern à Philadelphie, 15 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 34 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 16-4)
      March from Red Lion Tavern to Philadelphia. 3-4 September 1781. There was an extra day's halt in Philadelphia, the First Brigade departing on the 5th, the Second on the 6th. The "ancienne ligne Angloise," shown on the map beyond Kensington and to the north of the then-populated part of Philadelphia, extended from the mouth of Conoquonoque Creek on the Delaware (a bit to the north of the present Benjamin Franklin Bridge) westward to the height of land above the Schuyllkill now occupied by the Philadelphia Museum of Art; this line of fortifications, built by the British during their occupancy of the city in 1777-1778, ran approximately between present Callowhill and Spring Garden Streets. The map shows, upper right, the river forts: Billingsport and Red Bank (Fort Mercer) of the New Jersey shore of the Delaware, and Fort Miffin (of Mud Island) on the Pennsylvania side. General Rochambeau sailed down the river to Chester in order to inspect these forts; cf. Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, n. 83. The "Maison à Mr. le Ch[evali]er de la Luzern," shown on the map below the Falls of Schuyllkill, lower right, was "Laurel Hill" (also known as the Randolph Mansion), a country house rented by the Chevalier de la Luzerne, the French minister; it still stands on the bluff overlooking the Schuylkill in East Fairmount Park, between "Ormiston" and "Strawberry Mansion."
      MS, No. 16-4. [Rice/Brown, p. 145]
      See Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, p. 46, for an account of the march-past of the French army before the Continental Congress.
    - 58. de Philadelphie à Chester, 16 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 31.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 16-5)
      March from Philadelphia to Chester. 5-6 September 1781. The river, far left of map, is the Schuyllkill, with the pontoon bridge shown on the previous map. The route from Philadelphia, via Darby, to Checter is described in Itinerary 5. It was at Chester that Washington greeted Rochambeau (who had come down the Delaware from Philadelphia by boat) with the joyful news that de Grasse's fleet had arrived in the Chesapeake Bay; cf. Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, n. 85.
      MS, No. 16-5. [Rice/Brown, p. 145]
    - 59. de Chester à Willmington, 12 milles, et à Newport, 15 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 27.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 16-6)
      March from Chester [in Pennsylvania] to Wilmington and to Newport [in Delaware]. 6-7 September 1781. After Marcus Hook the route crossed Naaman Creek, several smaller streams, then the Brandywine, before entering Wilmington. As clearly shown here, Wilmington was originally built facing Christina Creek, according to a pattern similar to that of Philadelphia, with its Front Street along the Christina corresponding to Philadelphia's Front Street along the Delaware. The map indicates that one brigade (the Second) camped beyond Wilmington at Newport. The following year, when bound north, the army camped only at Newport (the four divisions in succession, 29 August-1 September 1782), and marched through Wilmington without halting there to camp; see No. 135.
      MS, No. 16-6. [Rice/Brown, p. 146]
    - 60. de Newport à head-of-Elk, 16 1/2 milles, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 35.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 16-7)
      March from Newport [in Delaware] to Head of Elk [in Maryland]. 7-8 September 1781. The route follows closely the "Old Baltimore Pike" (which has now been eclipsed in importance by U.S. Route 40 to the south of it and Interstate 95 to the north). Proceeding from the left of the map, "Whytly Crick" is White Clay Creek, "Christine Bridge" is now called Christiana, and "Couche's Bridge" is Cooch's Bridge, near which there stands today an eighteenth-century house still owned by the Cooch family. A monument by the bridge commemorates the "Battle of Cooch's Bridge," i.e., the skirmish of 3 September 1777 between Washington's troops and the British, led by Cornwallis, who had landed at Head of Elk and were proceeding towards the Brandywine and Philadelphia. Beyond Cooch's Bridge the route goes over Iron Hill, the height of land between the Delaware and the upper reaches of Chesapeake Bay. It was expected that the army would embark at Head of Elk.
      This is the last in the series of detailed road maps depicting the army's marches. Two blank leaves that follow it and that precede the last map in the "cahier" (the plan of Baltimore, No. 81) suggest that Berthier intended to continue and complete the series.
      MS, No. 16-7. [Rice/Brown, p. 146]
    - 81. Rade et port de Baltimore, undated; 1 item 22.5 x 20 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 16-8)
      Roadstead and Harbor at Baltimore. This map, included in the series of road maps for the 1781 marches (see note on No. 60), shows a larger area than map No. 80. It is extended eastward to include Whetstone Point and its fortifications (now Fort McHenry National Monument) and Gorsuch's Point opposite. In addition to the army units shown on No. 80, this one indicates four other regiments, lower right. Although the identifying colors have not been completed, these probably represent American regiments under General Lincoln.
      Other maps of Baltimore drawn the following year when the French army halted here from 24 July to 24 August 1782, are Nos. 129 to 130. The rapid growth of Baltimore during the decades following the Revolution may be traced by comparing Berthier's maps with the engraved map by A. P. Folie ("French Geographer"), "Plan of the Town of Baltimore and Its Environs" (1792), and with Warner and Hanna's engraved "Plan of the City and Environs of Baltimore" (1801).
      MS, No. 16-8. [Rice/Brown, p. 154]
    - 71. Ce gué dans sa plus grande profondeur peut avoir deux pieds et demi, undated; 1 item 14 x 15 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 17)
      Ford across the Delaware at Trenton. As stated on the map, "this ford at its greatest depth is about two and a half feet." The "Chateau," shown here as a directional point of reference, is Bloomsbury Court, the William Trent House, built ca. 1719, restored and still standing on South Warren Street. Cf. description of the ford in Itinerary 5. Clermont-Crèvecœur in his journal (p. 45) mentions that the crossing of the Delaware was made by both ford and ferry.
      MS, No. 17. [Rice/Brown, p. 150]
    - 82. Eldridge River l'une des Branches de Patapsco, undated; 1 item 13.5 x 22.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 18)
      Ford across the Elkridge River (near Baltimore). After leaving Baltimore and proceeding towards Spurrier's Tavern the army crossed the "Elkridge," i.e., the main branch of the Patapsco River, forming the boundary between Baltimore and Howard Counties. The ford, above the town then known as Elk Ridge Landing, is described in the note included on the map: "The detour that must be taken to cross by the ford is not great and I estimate the difference as about three-fourths of a mile, or a mile. The road leading to the ford is bad and filled with stones and foot-high stumps. As it approaches the ford the road is dangerous along the bank of the river, which is very deep in those places where the waters are damned up to operate the forges. This ford is very good if you pass between the big stones as marked here; if you stray from this line, you find large rocks and holes." ("Le détour quil faut faire pour passer au gué est tres peu de choses et j'estime la differénce a 3/4 de Mille ou 1 mille. Le chemin du gué est mauvais et rempli de Rochers et d'Arbres coupés a un pied de terre. En arrivant au gué il est dangereux suivant l'Escarpement de la Riviere qui est très profonde dans les Endroits ou les Eaux sont retenües pour faire aller les forges. - Ce gué est fort bon en cotoyant les grosses pierres cy marquées; lors qu'on s'en Ecarte on trouve de Grosses Roches et des Troüs.") The inscription, upper left, indicates that the little road up over the bluff ("la montagne") is "passable only for troops on foot."
      There is no map for the 35th camp at Spurrier's Tavern (16 September 1781), but see below, No. 128, which shows the camp made there on 23-26 August 1782 when the army was returning northward from Virginia.
      MS, No. 18. [Rice/Brown, pp. 154-155]
    - 120. Gué de Falmouth ... Chem de Frédérickbourg, Santier for manvais mais abrégeant de plus de moitié sur le grand chemin, undated; 1 item 17 x 27.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 19)